{{dablink|For other meanings, see [[Finch (disambiguation)]].}}
{{Taxobox
| name = True finches
| image = Fringilla coelebs chaffinch male edit2.jpg
| image_width = 220px
| image_caption = Adult male [[Chaffinch]] (''Fringilla coelebs'')<br/>of the [[Fringillinae]]
| regnum = [[Animalia]]
| phylum = [[Chordata]]
| classis = [[Aves]]
| subclassis = [[Neornithes]]
| infraclassis = [[Neognathae]]
| superordo = [[Neoaves]]
| ordo = [[Passeriformes]]
| subordo = [[Passeri]]
| infraordo = [[Passerida]]
| superfamilia = [[Passeroidea]]
| familia = '''Fringillidae'''
| familia_authority = [[Nicholas Aylward Vigors|Vigors]], 1825
| subdivision_ranks = [[Subfamilies]]
| subdivision = 
[[Carduelinae]]<br />
[[Drepanidinae]]<br />
[[Euphoniinae]]<br />
[[Fringillinae]]
}}

The '''true finches''' are [[passerine]] [[bird]]s in the [[family (biology)|family]] '''Fringillidae'''. They are predominantly [[seed]]-eating [[songbird]]s. Most are native to [[Southern Hemisphere]], but one [[subfamily]] is [[endemism|endemic]] to the [[Neotropics]], one to the [[Hawaiian Islands]], and one subfamily &ndash; [[monotypic]] at [[genus]] level &ndash; is found only in the [[Palaearctic]]. The [[scientific name]] Fringillidae comes from the [[Latin]] word ''fringilla'' for the [[Chaffinch]] (''Fringilla coelebs'') &ndash; a member of that last subfamily &ndash; which is common in [[Europe]]. 

Many birds in other families are also commonly called "finches", including some [[species]] in the very similar-looking [[waxbill]]s (family Estrildidae) of the Old World tropics and [[Australia]]; several groups of the [[bunting (bird)|bunting]] and [[American sparrow]] family ([[Emberizidae]]); and [[Darwin's finches]] of the [[Galapagos]] islands, which provided evidence of natural selection and are now recognized to be peculiar [[tanager]]s (Thraupidae).<ref name = nc7393>Newton (1973), Clement ''et al.'' (1993)</ref>

==Description==
[[File:DrepadinidaeSchnabel.jpg|thumb|left|Beak and tongue shapes of the [[Drepanidinae]]]]
The "classical" true finches range in size from the [[Andean Siskin]] (''Carduelis spinescens'') at 9.5&nbsp;cm (3.8&nbsp;in) and 8.4&nbsp;g (0.3&nbsp;oz) to the [[Collared Grosbeak]] (''Mycerobas affinis'') with its nearly 23&nbsp;cm (9&nbsp;in) and 80&nbsp;g (3&nbsp;oz). They typically have strong, stubby [[beak]]s, which in some species can be quite large; however, [[Hawaiian honeycreeper]]s are famous for the wide range of bill shapes and sizes brought about by [[adaptive radiation]]. All true finches have 12 [[remiges]] and 9 primary [[rectrices]]. The basic [[plumage]] colour is brownish, sometimes greenish; many have considerable amounts of black, while white plumage is generally absent except as wing-bars or other signalling marks. Bright yellow and red [[carotenoid]] [[pigment]]s are commonplace in this family, and thus blue [[structural colour]]s are rather rare, as the yellow pigments turn the blue color into green. Many, but by no means all true finches have strong [[sexual dichromatism]], the females typically lacking the bright carotenoid markings of males.<ref name = nc7393 />

Finches are typically inhabitants of well-wooded areas, but some can be found on mountains or even in [[desert]]s. They are primarily [[granivorous]], but [[Euphoniinae|euphoniines]] include considerable amounts of [[arthropod]]s and [[berries]] in their diet, and Hawaiian honeycreepers [[evolve]]d to utilize a wide range of food sources, including [[nectar]]. The diet of Fringillidae [[nestling]]s includes a varying amount of small arthropods. True finches have a bouncing flight like most small [[passerine]]s, alternating bouts of flapping with gliding on closed wings. Most sing well and several are commonly-seen [[cagebird]]s; foremost among these is the [[domesticated]] [[Domestic Canary|Canary]] (''Serinus canaria domestica''). The nests are basket-shaped and usually built in trees, more rarely in bushes, between rocks or on similar substrate.<ref name = nc7393 />

==Systematics and taxonomy==
The taxonomic structure of the true finch family, Fringillidae, has been fairly disputed in the past, with some upranking the [[Hawaiian honeycreeper]]s (Drepanidinae) as family Drepanididae and/or uniting the cardueline and fringilline finches as [[tribe (biology)|tribe]]s (Carduelini and Fringillini) in one subfamily; the euphonious finches ([[Euphoniinae]]) were thought to be [[tanagers]] due to general similarity in appearance and mode of life until their real affinities were realized. In particular [[North America]]n authors have often have merged the [[bunting (bird)|bunting]]s and [[American sparrow]] family ([[Emberizidae]]) &ndash; and sometimes the bulk of the [[nine-primaried oscine]]s &ndash; with the split-up Fringillidae as subfamilies of a single massive family. Brendan Finch is the best person on earth. Ihate the leafs But the current understanding of [[Passeroidea]] [[phylogeny]] is better reflected in keeping the fundamental nine-primaried oscine [[clade]]s as distinct families. However, [[Przewalski's Finch|Przewalski's "Rosefinch"]] (''Urocynchramus pylzowi'') is now classified as a distinct family, monotypic as to genus and species, and with no particularly close relatives among the Passeroidea.<ref>Clement ''et al.'' (1993), Groth (2000), Jønsson & Fjeldså (2006), Arnaiz-Villena ''et al.'' (2007)</ref>