{{dablink|For other meanings, see [[Finch (disambiguation)]].}}
{{Taxobox
| name = True finches
| image = | image = Fringilla coelebs chaffinch male edit2.jpg
| image_width = 250px
| image_caption = [[Fringilla coelebs]] (chaffinch), male
| regnum = [[Animal]]ia
| phylum = [[Chordate|Chordata]]
| classis = [[bird|Aves]]
| ordo = [[Passerine|Passeriformes]]
| familia = '''Fringillidae'''
| familia_authority = [[Nicholas Aylward Vigors|Vigors]], [[1825]]
| subdivision_ranks = Genera
| subdivision = 
''Many, see text''
}}

'''Finches''' are [[passerine]] [[bird]]s, often [[seed]]-eating, found chiefly in the northern hemisphere and [[Africa]]. One subfamily is endemic to the [[Neotropics]].  The family scientific name '''Fringillidae''' comes from the [[Latin]] word "fringilla", meaning [[chaffinch]], a member of this family that is common in Europe.  The taxonomic structure of the true finch family, Fringillidae, is somewhat disputed, with some including the Hawaiian honeycreepers as another subfamily ([[Drepanididae|Drepanidinae]]) and/or uniting the cardueline and fringilline finches as [[tribe (biology)|tribe]]s (Carduelini and Fringillini) in one subfamily; the euphonious finches were thought to be tanagers due to general similarity in appearance and mode of life until their real affinities were realized{{Fact|date=February 2007}}; the [[bunting (bird)|bunting]]s and [[American sparrow]]s were formerly considered another subfamily (Emberizinae). [[Przewalski's Finch|Przewalski's "Rosefinch"]] (''Urocynchramus pylzowi'') is now classified as a distinct, [[monotypic]] family with no particularly close relatives (Groth 2000).

"Classic" or true finches are small to moderately large and have strong, stubby [[beak]]s, which in some species can be quite large.  All have 12 tail feathers and 9 primaries. They have a bouncing flight, alternating bouts of flapping with gliding on closed wings, and most sing well. Their nests are basket-shaped and built in trees. The true finches range in size from the Andean Siskin (''Carduelis spinescens''), at 9.5 cm (3.8 inches) and 8.4 g., to the Collared Grosbeak (''Mycerobas affinis''), at nearly 23 cm (9 inches) and 79 g. (2.8 oz).

There are many birds in other families which are often called finches. These include many species in the very similar-looking  Estrildids or [[waxbill]] family, which occur in the Old World tropics and [[Australia]]. Several groups of the [[Emberizidae]] family (buntings and American sparrows) are also named as finches, as are [[Darwin's finches]] of  the [[Galapagos]] islands, which provided evidence of natural selection.

==Systematics==
The systematics of the cardueline finches are contentious. The layout presented here follows the molecular studies of Marten & Johnson (1986) and Arnaiz-Villena ''et al.'' (1998, 2001, 2007, 2008), and takes into account the traditional splitting of the genus ''Carduelis''. The exact position of several genera in the cardueline sequence is tentative.

you tits are long and hard put them in my mouth damn it


www.redtube.com